INSTRUCTOR: Hello, everyone,
and welcome to the content
video for Linux overview.
So Linux is the operating system
that we will be using heavily
in this course.
Linux, a few things about
Linux, in case you don't know,
Linux is very similar to
the Unix operating system,
which was developed in the '60s.
Soon after that,
Windows was developed
and then they eventually became
the three major operating
systems that are used today,
Linux, Unix and Windows.
So a little bit of
history on Linux and Unix.
So what you're
looking at right here,
this is all of the
branches that have come
from the Unix operating system.
So if you look on this, if you
can see where my mouse is right
here, 1969, that's
where Unix was
born, although it wasn't called
Unix until a couple of years
later.
So then Unix was born, and
the colors you're looking at,
the kind of orangish
color here, is
all of the mixed versions of
Unix that were some were sold
and some were not.
In the beginning, it was kind of
the wild west or a free for all
in terms of who
had a copy of Unix
and then would
develop their own.
The copyright laws for software
did not exist back then,
so it was common to share
or, quote unquote, steal.
Again, there weren't
the laws we have today,
so stealing might be a strong
word for what it was back then.
But however you
got it, there were
lots of branches that
came about from Unix.
So to explain this
tree a little bit here,
so the top here are the
first Unix operating systems.
And then they kind of branch
out into the operating systems
that were, on the
right-hand side here,
a lot of these are Sun.
So Sun Microsystems developed
their own operating system,
and then eventually Sun was
actually bought by Oracle,
and oracle owns the
Unix operating systems,
like Solaris right here, if
you can see where my mouse is.
Solaris is a huge operating
system that Oracle owns today.
And Oracle runs all things Java.
So it's Java.
For their enterprise
servers, they
will tell you it's
optimized to run on Solaris,
but really Java is
platform independent.
It can run anywhere.
Anyway, and then the
green ones, that's
the real focus of what I
want you to learn here.
So the green ones are the
free Unix operating systems,
are not run by a company.
They might be
managed or overseen,
but they're free and
open and available
and run by a community.
So the founder of Linux, which
is the operating system we're
going to use, if you
see where my mouse is
hovering here over on the
left, Linux was born in 1991.
And as you can see
here on this graph,
Linux did not branch off
from a version of Unix.
That's a common misconception.
Although, the founder of
Linux, let me show you him.
This is Linus Torvalds,
the founder of Linux.
He was heavily influenced by
Unix, both in the how it runs,
how it's used, and also
just the philosophy
of a operating system that was
free, open, and built and run
by a community rather
than a company.
So while not directly
a branch from Unix,
it is still heavily influenced
and very similar to Unix
in a lot of ways.
So that is Linux.
And again, because
Linux is free and became
such a stable and
robust operating system,
it became extremely popular
in professional use.
And then a company called
Red Hat came onto the scene,
and Red Hat is kind of all
bunched in, in all things Linux
right there.
Red Hat started to compete with
professional Unix operating
systems, and in
my opinion, really
put them not out of business,
but just destroyed their market
share in professional
server usage
today because Red
Hat was extremely
cheap because the operating
system itself was free
and you're paying
for the support of it
compared to the
other Unix operating
systems of the day, which
were much more expensive.
So Linux started
to just take over
Unix in the commercial
server world.
And it was adopted by AWS.
AWS has their own version of
Linux, Amazon Linux, which
is great, but we're I
prefer you to use Ubuntu,
just because Ubuntu is a little
easier to use and all of us
using Ubuntu will keep-- it's
easier to keep everything
in sync and we can share
commands with each other
and use it like that.
So Linux versus Windows,
why not Windows?
Again, Linux is free.
Windows, although
really Linux has
forced Windows to get a
lot cheaper over the years.
But Windows is still
not free, at least yet.
So Linux is free.
Linux is heavily used by
software developers and software
engineers and has proven to be
very stable, very robust, very
good operating system.
And the fact that it's free
makes it widely, widely popular.
So that is the operating
system used by AWS and one
we will also use here.
So Linux commands
in the terminal.
So the day-to-day
usage that you'll
have in this course with Linux
will be running your code
and also working in a terminal.
So in moving over to AWS now,
as you may or may not know,
you can open up a
terminal and then just
enter commands directly
into the command line here.
So here's your code, here's
the file browser on the left.
Your code is in the middle.
And then if you open up a
terminal by plus New Terminal
right there, then
you can directly
interact with the
operating system
through commands in a terminal.
All right.
So I went over to
GPT and I was curious
what GPT's thoughts on
what the most popular
20 Linux commands were.
So I threw that into--
and you can see on my screen.
I just asked it, but I'll just
ask it again and talk about them
as GPT starts cranking them out.
So I asked, what are the 20
most useful Linux commands?
And to me, the list
is almost perfect.
Whoop, error generating.
Well, let's try again.
Now I'm getting a connectivity.
That's OK.
This is like a cooking show.
When I ruin the cake, when I'm
making a cake and I ruin it,
there's already one in the
oven that I can show you.
So here it is.
So here's the 20 most useful
Linux commands according to GPT.
And honestly, I love the list.
So ls, cd, mkdir, remove, copy,
move, cat, grep are all those
are all commands I use almost
daily within a Linux terminal.
The only one on here
that I really don't--
GPT was almost perfect.
The one really not is ifconfig.
Ifconfig, if you're a system
administrator or a network
administrator, then yeah, you're
going to use ifconfig daily.
But ifconfig is a configure
network interfaces,
which you're not really
going to be doing a lot.
So last time I used
ifconfig was when
I was working for Bank of
America's investment bank
and trying to figure
out why computers
couldn't talk to each other.
So it is useful if you're
troubleshooting network things
or working on network things.
But honestly, other
than that, this list
is fantastic and will
really be heavily the list
that you use day to day.
So to just play around, I'll
just grab the first four here.
So ls, cd, mkdir, and remove.
So if you go into a
terminal here and do an ls,
it'll give you a listing of
everything in your directory
that you're in.
And you can see right there--
let me do another one
on that list, pwd.
So pwd stands for print
working directory and that
tells me I'm in HOME
Ubuntu environment.
And let me point out something
about HOME Ubuntu environment
in AWS.
When you create a Cloud9
environment, you give it a name,
it gives that the location
of that folder's name.
The-- excuse me.
It assigns that folder to
HOME Ubuntu environment.
So in other words, I named
this environment data 5500.
That is the folder HOME Ubuntu
environment on the file system.
So when I do a pwd, it's
HOME Ubuntu environment.
And then when I
do an ls, you can
see it's got all of the same
folders you see on the left
here, so data 5500
code, data 5500
file 22, data 5500 spring 2023.
All of those are the
same things you see when
you do an ls in the terminal.
So that's kind of how you
can keep an eye on things
to make sure
everything's matching up
in the terminal and
the file system,
not that you really need to
because the terminal will
be correct.
Another command that's
really useful is mkdir.
So I'm going to do
mkdir Andy test,
and that creates a new folder.
So if you look over to the left,
now there's mkdir Andy test
and there's nothing
in there yet.
I'm going to do a
cd into Andy test.
Now do a pwd, you'll see that
I'm in HOME Ubuntu environment
Andy test.
And I can do an ls in here.
There's nothing in here yet, but
I can do an echo, hello world,
and redirect that to test.txt.
And you can see now
I've got my test.txt.
hello world right there
from my echo command.
So that's-- and one more command
I probably should show you here
is a pip3 install NumPy, which
I already have NumPy installed,
but, hey, it's getting me NumPy.
There you go.
I guess I didn't.
That's interesting.
So pip3 is a very another very
useful command for this course
because you're going to be where
you're going to be using Python
and you're going to need
all of the libraries
that you'll install with pip.
Another note,
though, pip3 refers
to Python 3's version of pip.
So these are 2018
Ubuntu servers.
So when you just
run pip, it's going
to give you the 2018 or
Python 2 version of pip,
which Python 2 has been end of
life and decommissioned already.
So it's not in
production anymore.
So that is one little
annoying thing that you'll
have to kind of just
remember is you'll
have to use pip3, not pip.
But hopefully AWS gets around to
upgrading their Ubuntu servers
and you don't have to deal
with pip anymore, or with pip3.
You can just call it pip.
But for now, use pip3 to install
any of your Python libraries.
OK.
I think that is
about it for Linux.
And again, there's so much
awesome documentation on Linux
out there, which means
that that documentation has
been trained by GPT.
So GPT is a fantastic
resource for trying
to figure out things or
learn things or troubleshoot
things in Linux and AWS, but
specifically the documentation
is going to be much,
much wider for Linux.
So highly recommend you use
GPT to work through all things
Linux.
And that's it.
Oh, one more thing.
So now that you know a little
more about Unix and Linux, now
you will better understand a
funny scene in Wayne's World 2.
This is Wayne's World 2, when
Garth and Betty Jo fall in love,
and check it out.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
- That's a Unix book.
- Yeah.
- Cool.
[END PLAYBACK]
INSTRUCTOR: That's a Unix book.
Yeah.
Cool.
Now you understand that
it's an operating system
and that Garth and Betty
Jo in Wayne's World 2--
Garth and Betty Jo in
Wayne's World 2 fall in love
over a Unix book.
That's it.
That concludes
our content video.
Thanks for watching.